let set15=
[
    {
        question:`#1. Which of the following statements is not correct about deforestation?`,
        options:
        [
            'A. Deforestation increases the temperature on the earth.',
'B. Ground water level gets lowered.',
'C. The soil properties remain unaffected.',
'D. The water holding capacity of soil is lowered.',
        ],
        answer:`Answer: C`,
        exp:`Explanation: Deforestation means that less carbon dioxide will be taken up by the plants, resulting in increase in its amount in the atmosphere. This will lead to global warming as carbon dioxide traps the heat rays reflected by the earth.Deforestation also lowers the ground water level. The major reason behind the changes of soil properties is deforestation. This causes soil erosion. Soil erosion lowers the content of humus in soil and soil fertility also declines. Soil erosion also causes desertification.Deforestation adversely affects the water holding capacity of the soil. The movement of water from the soil surface into the ground (infiltration rate) is reduced. This is responsible for floods.`
    },
    {
        question:`#2. Consider the following statements: \n 1. The plants and animals found in a particular area are termed flora and fauna of that area. \n 2. Endemic species are those species of plants and animals which are found exclusively in a particular area. \n Which of the statements given above is/are correct?`,
        options:
        [
            'A. 1 only',
'B. 2 only',
'C. Both 1 and 2',
'D. Neither 1 nor 2',
        ],
        answer:`Answer: C`,
        exp:`Explanation: The plants and animals found in a particular area are termed as flora and fauna of that area. Endemic species are those species of plants and animals which are found exclusively in a particular area. They are not naturally found anywhere else.`
    },
    {
        question:`#3. To protect the flora, fauna and their habitat; certain protected areas have been marked. Which of the following protected areas is/are correctly matched? \n 1. Sanctuaries: Places where killing (poaching) or capturing of animals is strictly prohibited. \n National Parks: Protected areas for the wildlife, where they can live freely and utilise the natural resources. \n 2. Biosphere Reserves: The biosphere reserves help to maintain the variety of plants, animals and microorganisms along with the culture generally found in an area. \n Which of the statements given above is/are correct?`,
        options:
        [
            'A. 1 and 2 only',
'B. 2 only',
'C. 1 and 3 only',
'D. 1, 2 and 3',
        ],
        answer:`Answer: D`,
        exp:`Explanation: Of the various places meant for the protection of the flora and fauna, sanctuaries, national parks and biosphere reserves are the primary. Wildlife sanctuaries provide protection and suitable living conditions to wild animals. Sanctuaries are places where killing (poaching) or capturing of animals is strictly prohibited. Hence, the wildlife and their habitat are protected from any form of interference. The local population and certain human interference is allowed, which makes it different from biosphere reserves. National Parks are protected spaces for the wildlife, where any form of human interference is prohibited. Hence, the wildlife can freely live here and utilise the natural resources. The biosphere reserves help to maintain the variety of plants, animals and microorganisms along with the culture generally found in an area. A biosphere reserve is so large that it can have several protected areas within it. These protected areas are constructed to protect the biodiversity of a specific area. A biosphere reserve also protects the culture of a given area. To protect our flora and fauna and their habitats, protected areas called sanctuaries, national parks and biosphere reserves have been earmarked. Plantation, cultivation, grazing, felling trees, hunting. Biodiversity refers to the various types of species plants, animals and microbes present in a particular area. Bharatpur Sanctuary, Kaziranga National Park, Bhadra Wildlife Sanctuary, Great Nicobar Biosphere Reserve are some of the examples of protected areas.`
    },
    {
        question:`#4. Consider the following statements about Pachmarhi Biosphere Reserve: \n 1. The Pachmarhi Biosphere Reserve consists of one national park named Pench and two wildlife sanctuaries called Bori and Pachmarhi. \n 2. Bison, Indian giant squirrel and Flying squirrel are the Endemic Fauna of Pachmarhi Biosphere reserve. \n 3. Rock shelters are also found inside the Satpura National Park. These are the prehistoric evidences of human life in these jungles. They give us an idea of the life of the primitive people. Rock paintings are found in these shelters. \n Which of the statements given above is/are correct?`,
        options:
        [
            'A. 1 and 2 only',
'B. 2 and 3 only',
'C. 3 only',
'D. 1, 2 and 3',
        ],
        answer:`Answer: B`,
        exp:`Explanation: Statement 1 is not correct because the Pachmarhi Biosphere Reserve consists of one national park named Satpura and two wildlife sanctuaries named Bori and Pachmarhi. Satpura National Park is India’s first Reserve forest. The best form of teak is found in this region. Bison, Indian giant squirrel and Flying squirrel are the Endemic Fauna of Pachmarhi Biosphere reserve; and Sal and wild mango are the Endemic Flora. Sal, teak, mango, jamun, silver ferns, arjun, etc are the flora and chinkara, blue-bull, barking deer, cheetah, leopard, wild dog, wolf, etc. are examples of the fauna of the Pachmarhi Biosphere Reserve. Rock shelters are also found inside the Satpura National Park. Rock paintings are found in these shelters.`
    },
    {
        question:`#5. Which of the following statements is/are correct regarding the Red Data Book? \n 1. It is a book which records all the Endemic Species of a region. \n 2. It is a book where the records of Biosphere Reserves are maintained. \n 3. It is a book which maintains the records of all the endangered species. \n Select the correct option from the codes given below:`,
        options:
        [
            'A. Only 1 and 2',
'B. Only 1 and 3',
'C. Only 3',
'D. 1, 2 and 3',
        ],
        answer:`Answer: C`,
        exp:`Explanation: Red Data book is a book which maintains a record of all the endangered species. There are separate Red Data Books for plants, animals and other organisms.The endangered species are protected in Wildlife sanctuaries. Large and small, all types of animals are protected in these sanctuaries, because their contribution to the ecosystem cannot be ignored. Small organisms face the danger of extinction much more than larger animals.`
    },
    {
        question:`#6. Which of the following is/are part of the ecosystem?`,
        options:
        [
            'A. All trees and plants',
'B. All organisms and microorganisms',
'C. Non-living constituents',
'D. All of the above',
        ],
        answer:`Answer: D`,
        exp:`Explanation: For any given area, all the plants, trees, organisms, microorganisms, non living things, like water, soil, river, delta, sunlight, etc together comprise of the ecosystem.`
    },
    {
        question:`#7. Which of the following statement is related to the Ex situ conservation? `,
        options:
        [
            'A. Established protected area network, with appropriate management practices, corridors to link fragments restore degraded habitats within and outside. ',
'B. Established botanical and zoological gardens conservation stands, bank of germ plasma pollen, seed, seedlings, tissue culture, gene and DNA etc. ',
'C. Agriculture is totally dependent on ecosystem processes and functions provided by biodiversity soil formation, nutrient cycling, and pollination of crops maintaining water cycles ',
'D. None of the above',
        ],
        answer:`Answer: B`,
        exp:`Explanation: Ex-situ conservation involves maintenance and breeding of endangered plants and animals under partially or wholly controlled conditions in specific areas including zoo, gardens, nurseries, etc. That is, the conservation of selected plants and animals in selected areas outside their natural habitat is known as ex-situ conservation. The stresses on living organisms due to competition for food, water, space etc. can be avoided by ex-situ conservation there by providing conditions necessary for a secure life and breeding. For ex-situ conservations the species to be conserved should be identified followed by adoption of different ex-situ methods such as, longterm captive breeding and propagation for the species which have lost their habitats permanently, short-term propagation and release of the animals in their natural habitat, animal translocation and reintroduction and advanced technology in the service of endangered species. The different advantages of ex-situ conservation are, 1. It gives longer life time and breeding activity to animals 2. Genetic techniques can be utilized in the process 3. Captivity breed species can again be reintroduced in the wild The ex-situ conservation strategies include botanical gardens, zoological gardens, conservation stands and gene, pollen, seed, seedling, tissue culture and DNA banks. Seed gene banks make the easiest way to store germplasm of wild and cultivated plants at low temperature. While in field gene banks, preservation of genetic resources is being done under normal growing conditions.`
    },
    {
        question:`#8. On which date International Day for Biodiversity is observed?`,
        options:
        [
            'A. May, 15',
'B. May, 20',
'C. May, 22',
'D. June, 5',
        ],
        answer:`Answer: C`,
        exp:`Explanation: The United Nations has proclaimed May 22 The International Day for Biological Diversity (IDB) to increase understanding and awareness of biodiversity issues. When first created by the Second Committee of the UN General Assembly in late 1993, 29 December (the date of entry into force of the Convention of Biological Diversity), was designated The International Day for Biological Diversity. In December 2000, the UN General Assembly adopted 22 May as IDB, to commemorate the adoption of the text of the Convention on 22 May 1992 by the Nairobi Final Act of the Conference for the Adoption of the Agreed Text of the Convention on Biological Diversity. This was partly done because it was difficult for many countries to plan and carry out suitable celebrations for the date of 29 December, given the number of holidays that coincide around that time of year.`
    },
    {
        question:`#9. Find out the correct definition of 'Biodiversity'.`,
        options:
        [
            'A. The variety of plant and animal life in the world or in a particular habitat, a high level of which is usually considered to be important and desirable.',
'B. It encompasses the interaction of all living species. Climate, weather, and natural resources that affect human survival and economic activity.',
'C. Both A & B',
'D. None of the above',
        ],
        answer:`Answer: A`,
        exp:`Explanation: The term biodiversity (from “biological diversity”) refers to the variety of life on Earth at all its levels, from genes to ecosystems, and can encompass the evolutionary, ecological, and cultural processes that sustain life. Biodiversity is important to most aspects of our lives. We value biodiversity for many reasons, some utilitarian, some intrinsic. This means we value biodiversity both for what it provides to humans, and for the value it has in its own right. Utilitarian values include the many basic needs humans obtain from biodiversity such as food, fuel, shelter, and medicine. Further, ecosystems provide crucial services such as pollination, seed dispersal, climate regulation, water purification, nutrient cycling, and control of agricultural pests. Biodiversity also holds value for potential benefits not yet recognized, such as new medicines and other possible unknown services. Biodiversity has cultural value to humans as well, for spiritual or religious reasons for instance. The intrinsic value of biodiversity refers to its inherent worth, which is independent of its value to anyone or anything else. This is more of a philosophical concept, which can be thought of as the inalienable right to exist. Finally, the value of biodiversity can also be understood through the lens of the relationships we form and strive for with each other and the rest of nature. We may value biodiversity because of how it shapes who we are, our relationships to each other, and social norms. These relational values are part of peoples’ individual or collective sense of wellbeing, responsibility for, and connection with the environment. The different values placed on biodiversity are important because they can influence the conservation decisions people make every day.`
    },
    {
        question:`#10. What does the term 'MIKE' stands for?`,
        options:
        [
            'A. Monitoring of Illegal Killing of Elephants',
'B. Monitoring of Illegal Killing in Europe',
'C. Monitoring of Illegal Killing of Eagle',
'D. Monitoring of Illegal Killing of Endangered Species',
        ],
        answer:`Answer: A`,
        exp:`Explanation: The Monitoring the Illegal Killing of Elephants (MIKE) programme is an international collaboration that measures the levels, trends and causes of elephant mortality, thereby providing an information base to support international decision-making related to conservation of elephants in Asia and Africa. The MIKE Programme was established by the Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species of Wild Fauna and Flora (CITES) by Resolution 10.10 adopted at the tenth Conference of the Parties in 1997. There are currently 28 sites participating in the MIKE programme in Asia, distributed across 13 countries: India has 10 sites, followed by two sites each in Cambodia, Indonesia, Lao PDR, Malaysia, Myanmar and Thailand, and one site each in Bangladesh, Bhutan, China, Nepal, Sri Lanka and Viet Nam. In 2017, IUCN was engaged by CITES to implement the MIKE Asia programme in two sub-regions: South Asia (via the IUCN India Country Office in New Delhi); and Southeast Asia (through the IUCN Asia Regional Office in Bangkok). This forms part of the wider Asia Wildlife Law Enforcement and Demand Reduction Management Project funded by the European Union.`
    }
]